

Curriculum Vitae for Ada Ortiz-Carbonell

Personal information

Address: Colletts gate 59 E-mail: ada@xal.no

0456 Oslo Phone: +47 98887847

Born: 7th January 1975

Summary

I hold a PhD in Physics from 2003 specializing in Solar Physics. I have 20 years of experience in data processing, image analysis, time-series analysis, spectral analysis and analytical models. With time I have expanded my research subjects and used different methods including statistical data analysis. I have additionally explored various topics within machine learning. I consider myself very perseverant and used to overcome adversity in a scientific environment by being creative, hard-working, and having an analytical mindset. Excellence, accuracy and detail define my scientific work. I have well-proven organisational capabilities. My colleagues regard me as an excellent communicator and an all-terrain asset. I have experience in leading international collaborations, management of grants, student mentoring and scientific outreach.

Technical skills

Frameworks Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib Languages Python, IDL, Matlab, Fortran, LaTeX

Scientific skills Image analysis, pattern recognition, anomaly detection, analysis of

time series, analytical modelling, statistical analysis

Tools Mac OS X, Unix, Linux, Git

Education

2000 - 2003	PhD in Physics. University of Barcelona (Spain). Thesis title: "Solar
	irradiance variations induced by faculae and small magnetic elements
	in the photosphere". Cum Laude by unanimity.
1997 - 2000	Research Proficiency. University of Barcelona (Spain)
1993 - 1997	Licentiate in Physics. University of Barcelona (Spain)

Professional experience

2004 - 2006	Postdoctoral fellow. High Altitude Observatory, National Center for
	Atmospheric Research, (Boulder, USA)
2007 – 2010	Postdoctoral fellow . Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, (Norway)
2013 – 2014	Lecturer. Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, (Norway)
2015 – 2017	Visiting Scientist. Instituto de Astrofísica de Andalucía (IAA-CSIC), (Spain)
2010 – 2019	Senior researcher. Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University
2019 –	of Oslo, (Norway) Data scientist. Expert Analytics (Oslo, Norway)

Languages

mother tongue
fluent
intermediate
intermediate
mother tongue

Personal skills

Analitycal thinking	I have the ability to tackle the unknown by collecting the necessary data, analyzing and interpreting it, obtaining results using cross-disciplinary methods, and present them in an easy-to-understand way.	
Communication and writing skills	I am regarded by my peers as an excellent speaker, both in scientific talks to an specialized audience or in educating the public. Proven experience in writing scientific documents (30 published articles). I have been nominated by my peers to become a TED speaker.	
Complex problem solving	I like applying creativity to break down complex problems into smaller parts that can be tackled in an easier way, while keeping the big picture in mind. Combine methods from different disciplines to solve problems.	
Leadership	Thanks to holding a few research grants involving international collaborations, I have earned experience as project leader and manager. I also feel comfortable as team member where I am organized, structured and a responsible player.	
Organizational skills	I have well-proven experience as organizer for several international conferences and schools, where I have done everything from managing the logistical aspects, setting up the conference's websites and	

planning the scientific programmes.

Teaching and outreach

Being Lecturer provided me with the ability to explain difficult material in an understandable language for the non-expert. I have significant experience in outreach, explaining complex science to the general public. Examples of this are invitations to deliver public talks at Queen's University Belfast (UK) and the University of Oslo (Norway) aimed for a general audience. Moreover I am editor of two outreach books and have written a popular science article in the Spanish newspaper El País.

Versatile and all-terrain

I feel comfortable whether it is scientific, administration, logistics, organisation or managing tasks.

Some interests and hobbies

Scientific Outreach officer in Norway for the European Solar Telescope project, outreach Astronomy on Tap (astronomy for the general public), as well as re-

gular educative outreach talks & events for the general public

Sports Alpine skiing, scuba diving, martial arts, white-water rafting

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Observing and understanding flux emergence using IRIS and SST coor-

dinated data. Research project funded by the Research Council of Nor-

way.

Period 2016-2019

Role Principal Investigator

Staffing 2 members and 5 collaborators

Description This effort aimed at studying how magnetic fields living in the interior

> of the Sun rise up and trespass the surface of the star while continuing their journey up through the solar atmosphere. In this project, I combined large data sets (images and spectra) both from spacecrafts and ground-based observatories and pre-processed them. In addition, I was in charge of carrying out the data analysis, which required developing specific scientific coding for image analysis, spectral analysis, statistical analysis, and comparison with numerical simulations. I was responsible for several scientific articles published in peer-reviewed journals and for presentation of the results in international conferences.

Activity Space and ground-based observations of the solar atmosphere. Rese-

arch project funded by the Research Council of Norway.

Period 2011-2013

Role Principal Investigator, Project leader

Staffing me, with 4 collaborators Description

The goal of this project was to study the lower part of the solar atmosphere at the highest spatial resolution. Both the dynamics and magnetism of the physical processes going on in the surface were studied. For this project I pre-processed large astronomical data sets of images and spectra (cleaning the data from instrumental effects and making them ready-to-use). I developed the programming codes in order to analyse images, time series, create feature tracking algorithms, and statistical data analysis. I was the main author in the resulting articles published in international peer-reviewed journals, and presentations in conferences.

Activity Science communication and outreach. EST Communication Officer for

Norway.

Period 2017 -

Role member of organising committee

Staffing 4 members

Description I am in charge of organizing and managing a series of posts in social

media about the Sun and the European Solar Telescope (EST) project in order to educate the general public about the importance of studying our nearest star. Through this project I delivered public lectures at Queen's University Belfast and the University of Oslo aimed for the general public. I am editor of two books for the EST project with the goal of educating society in the Sun and the Universe. Also in charge of dissemination activities in Norway related to the EST project.

Activity Organisation of international conferences and schools

Period 2010 - 2018 Role co-organizer Staffing 2 members

Description I have organised 7 schools and international conferences since 2010.

My tasks involved everything from planning the scientific programme, managing the logistical aspects, being in charge of the conference's websites and designing the logos and banners. In addition to these, I have been convener of 2 symposia as well as chairperson of 10+

sessions.

Activity European Solar Telescope Science Advisory Group member. Infrastruc-

ture and technological project funded by the EU H2020 Framework

Period 2017 Role core member
Staffing 21 members

Description Here we define the scientific questions that will be tackled by the next

generation 4 meter class European Solar Telescope. This project is an infrastructure, technological and scientific challenge of pan-European dimensions involving 16 countries and 23 scientific institutions. Budget = 200 MEuros, financed under the EU H2020 Framewok. My task as a core member is to envision the questions about the Sun that will be interesting in 10 years and design the necessary instrumentation.

expert**analytics.**no